[SPEAKER_02]: Where do you have in mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: I was thinking the difference between samatha and vipassana.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where do you think the difference is?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I think it... it relates to what we've been talking about in previous talks, in recent talks.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, eh... samatha...
[SPEAKER_02]: It seems to be more about unifying and composing the mind, recognizing the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you compose your mind without understanding what the mind is?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you compose the mind without seeing the mind and just by following an external set of prescriptions of how to compose your mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that even conceivable?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can you then compose your mind spontaneous?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you compose your mind unknowingly?
[SPEAKER_01]: Unknowingly, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what do all these things have in common then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Vipassana.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can you compose the mind without understanding of the mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's no samatha without vipassana?
[SPEAKER_01]: And the reason why I ask that is because, you know, I don't know how many times I myself heard it from different people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, a general contemporary view of... oh, you do your vipassana.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not referring to the meditation technique of vipassana, but, like, study.
[SPEAKER_01]: You do your study, and now it's time for formal meditation, whereby you go and you follow, like, watch your nostrils, and somehow what you studied
[SPEAKER_01]: will miraculously fit into this experience of non-thinking and observing sensations.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's absolutely two completely different things, aren't there?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you see no relationship between samatha and vipassana, they are not two yokes of the same thing as the Buddha described.
[SPEAKER_01]: They are completely two different yokes.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not even yokes because they're not pulling anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, they are yokes of the wrong view, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wrong idea of samatha and wrong idea of vipassana are reinforcing your wrong views of what practice is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you are yoking yourself, just the other way.
[SPEAKER_02]: My experience, it was maybe more, you do your samatha,
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you need to calm your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, once it's calm enough, you now direct your mind to the nature of... And, and, funnily enough, all of that is completely refuted by the Buddha in, in Samādhi-tsutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's absolutely no such thing as right meditation without a right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, here you are, starting your practice, thinking what you do as a meditation is the meditation that pertains to the meditation of enlightenment or whatever it is teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Knowingly, at the same time, you know that you have no right view, but you're thinking, my meditation is right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is that... what would be the sole criteria, then, for those people, for people who engage in such a contradictory view, yet adhere to a certain method or technique of the meditation, knowing at the same time that they don't have the right view, they don't know what the mind is, they don't understand the nature of the mind, yet they're practicing calming of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the criteria for that calming?
[SPEAKER_01]: How nice it feels!
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasure, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what we had said again and again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without the right view, you'll be just meditating with your own sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot possibly not meditate without it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not a meditation that he approves of.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, think of samatha as calm vipassana and think of vipassana as active samatha.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, it seems to me that I still see two, like, sort of different directions, or like, slight different perspective, or orientation, involved in the samatha-vipassana distinction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Go on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Describe.
[SPEAKER_02]: All that can manifest, manifests as an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: And any notion of something outside of that is also another image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Clarifying that mind comes first, that direction seems to be about what samatha is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whereas, I would say, vipassana seems to be more...
[SPEAKER_02]: I guess they are totally linked, but vipassana is more about the fact that whatever image, whatever has manifested...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, you just said that clarifying that thought is what samādhi is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Clarifying that thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what vipassana is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Clarifying that mind comes first, understanding the nature of
[SPEAKER_01]: In a reasonably enduring image, that any other relationship, any other movement, any other thought in regard to it, must be within the fundamentally manifested enduring image.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what vipassana is.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're just discerning it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And see, they're so linked together, that you thought you were describing one, while you were describing the other.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I keep thinking of vipassana as being more about the fact that I didn't, I can't own this image, this, whatever, whatever, whatever has manifested, sort of, I was subjected to it, rather than I create, you know, I can't own this.
[SPEAKER_02]: That, to me, seems...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what's the summit then?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, samādhi is more about including the totality of your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, not...
[SPEAKER_02]: Including what?
[SPEAKER_02]: Including, like, so, as an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: As...
[SPEAKER_02]: Including what you just clarified.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, it's not the opposite direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, it's not the opposite direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't have one without the other.
[SPEAKER_02]: Different emphasis of the same... Yeah, that's what I'm... yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But there is a different emphasis there.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why there are two.
[SPEAKER_01]: Two balls of one yoke.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody says they're one thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, literally, if one ball pulls harder, the other one is pulled by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They cannot be separated.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no yoke without two.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, what general attitude is, it's basically two separate balls with two separate yokes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, like, somehow they magically connect.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, let's... let me try and put it another way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only way to discern the two is within one.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it was said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Two balls are tied with one yoke.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you are approaching... you're trying to discern yoke by chasing two different balls, you're not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, you need to understand what yoking is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you'll see the two aspects of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you'll know where the two balls are.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you'll be practicing samatha, developing vipassana, vipassana, then maintain samatha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: And some of the most accurately would be what you just said, discernment is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you discern the image has to endure first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter the secondary action, choices, intentions, and so on, that come... will be within and you stop assuming outside of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your now clarified, discerned context.
[SPEAKER_01]: That also endures.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, the things that have arisen on their own were enduring, that allowed you to discern the nature of enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, your discernment endures.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maintaining the endurance of your discernment is what Samatha is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why your discernment will come to fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why in jhānas, you fully fulfill your understanding of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you come there with the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's exactly what's enduring, the clarity.
[SPEAKER_02]: But could you say, then, could you say that the the recognizing the unknown ability of what's manifested, is more an aspect of vipassana, or the direction of vipassana, but, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you're not applying it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're applying it, it means you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not discerning it on account of the reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the reason why it feels like it's a separate direction is because you keep interjecting yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's doing something.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you have the discernment of vipassana you talk about, within that, discern the samatha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't do it elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's my point.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, it's not accurate even on that entirely internal, personal, slight shift of your attention.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let alone how inaccurate it is when you do it as a separate thing, my study and my meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's earth and sky.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when I, like, when we usually do it, oh, how are you feeling right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the presently enduring feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what are the characteristics?
[SPEAKER_01]: of the present enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: The characteristics... Just your current mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Describe me the characteristics of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the nature, not in the content.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right now, it feels a bit bland.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bland.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are the kind of symptoms of blandness, so to speak?
[SPEAKER_01]: A lack of... A lack of... A lack.
[SPEAKER_02]: A certain lack.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, see, now you're basically discerning and looking and lifting up and looking around of one thing that endures.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, imagine I ask you, what is your current present enduring feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm asking you that again now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: Neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... And now?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the presently enduring feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: Neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we keep talking about, and I keep asking you a few times, you're not actively thinking about the present enduring, but you're not ignoring it either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's there, enduring.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the samatha aspect of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not actively engaging with what's enduring, but you're still aware of its enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why mindfulness, developed correctly, result in proper, that's why samādhi developed correctly, result in fulfilling all four foundations of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And no one would, no one would think that you could do vipassana without mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nobody would think what you mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: No one would...
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't think anyone would... and no one would argue... that you can do vipassana without mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why you can't have too much of mindfulness either, in the same way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a basis for what you want to discern, or it's a basis for maintaining the enduring image of what you discerned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, mindfulness has to be there, and you can't do too much of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can, as the Buddha said, you can do too much of vipassana.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can do too much of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, when you don't make enough effort to think about the characteristics which remain to a degree unclear.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, you can be thinking a bit too much to a degree that you're becoming a bit nervous and restless and not calm.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, you kind of... because you're so engaged with characteristics of whatever is presently enduring, you're forgetting the present enduring thing is enduring there on its own and it doesn't require your effort of upholding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you get a bit restless.
[SPEAKER_01]: But either way, with the right view, it will even itself out.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will have to even itself up.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it has to, yeah, that's what it says.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or stay steady.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even itself up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Evenly yoked.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yoked together.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Something possibly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're holding something and then it's... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to keep... Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: To see what's going on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, you don't have to...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's calming.
[SPEAKER_01]: It calms down, literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, so it's certainly me.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, samatha is more of that kind of passive, not ignoring the background.
[SPEAKER_02]: Passive, non-ignoring, not engaging in with the right order of things that you just discerned.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which you couldn't do without the vipassana.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you wouldn't be discerning it if it wasn't there endurance.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you haven't recognized the degree of its endurance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And samatha is not so much
[SPEAKER_01]: You then doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more the fact that these things are jobs.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the perfect samatha that the Buddha described is the jhānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The one that he always praised.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why there is no sense of I am in them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even for somebody who is still not an arahant, that sense has to subside completely before you get to develop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can't be doing it and it's about you not doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's so pleasant and sublime and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it doesn't require effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it develops discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, with right view, you get jhānas, you will be at least anāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, you get jhānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you develop your mind to the extent of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would be free from sensuality and probably free from conceit in no time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's just becoming fully familiar with the... as in, as solid as a rock, steady, the clarity of things that you discern.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just becomes your mode of being.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it fully becomes apparent, clear, beyond doubt, that, oh, there is no room for any.
[SPEAKER_01]: The slightest degree of me and I am, and me choosing to do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, whatever I do, these things are enjoying.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the sole reason that it felt like two different directions for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even they were unified with the general context.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, it wasn't as accurate enough, because you still had a trace of idea of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I apply it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you don't apply it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You applying it, it's a separate thing now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you can take me applying something, as there is an image that is used for you, which gives the context of your application.
[SPEAKER_01]: But your vipassana and samādhi are on the level of there is an image, not on the level of your application of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, no, you can't have too much of it, the right mindfulness, and it's a necessary basis for any form of application or discernment.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, I mean, I imagine most people think samatha and vipassana is coming a step backwards, but people think that they're techniques.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so these two things I do.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you have none if you don't have the right view first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, Samādhi to Sutta, many other suttas as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't possibly practice rightly without knowing what the right practice is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's such a hard thing for people to accept as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it feels like, oh, so whatever I've been doing means it doesn't count for anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you don't know what it... you will only know whether it counts for something or not once you get the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: In hindsight, you can see whether your practice is counted or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: By you being too afraid to admit that it might not count for anything, it's basically what's going to hinder you from finding what does count for something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just simply that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fear that you might be... Yeah, even if you wasted all of your time, 20 years of your supposed practice, it's never too late.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if the practice was right, you have nothing to fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why are you fearing questioning it?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't lose from practicing more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are you going to lose?
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only lose from refraining to practice further because of fear of what you thought you invested in beforehand.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just, I think, for people, those people, it's less painful to...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's less painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, it boils down to the criteria that Buddha said Bhutujjana would only know, which is, this pleases me, and this thing displeases me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why I follow it, that's why I reject it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like even, even intellect and reasoning are heavily rooted in pleasing, displeasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I'm for it, that's why I'm against it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, that's why I find arguments for it, that's why I find arguments against it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just because it pleases me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they remain ignorant of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's why they help abuse.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you're following the right teaching, you're following for the wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.